Guide to the Abraham Yates, Jr. papers, 1604-1825 [bulk 1760-1796]
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division.
Abraham Yates, Jr. papers
1604-1825
1760-1796
3405
MssCol 3405
Yates, Abraham, 1724-1796
The New York Public Library. Manuscripts and Archives Division. Stephen A. Schwarzman Building Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, New York, NY 10018-2788
2.2 linear feet (5 boxes, 1 v.)
Abraham Yates, Jr. (1724-1796) was an American politician and pamphleteer. A radical Whig who was elected to New York provincial congresses and conventions, he was chairman of the convention (1776-1777) which drafted the first state constitution, served as a state senator from 1777 to 1790, and was mayor of Albany from 1790 to 1796. He wrote anti-federalist pamphlets with his relative, jurist Robert Yates (1738-1801), under the pen-name The Rough Hewer. Collection consists of correspondence, writings, speeches, notes, estate papers, photograph, and printed matter. Correspondence, 1754-1825, concerns the activities of Abraham Yates as a political figure in New York State. Writings, notes and speeches include essays he wrote on the U.S. Constitution, notes on proceedings in Congress, speeches to the delegates to Congress in 1786, The Rough Hewer manuscript, and notes for histories of New York and Albany. Also, papers relating to the Manor of Rensselaerwyck and the Albany Committee of Correspondence, land and family records, photograph of painting of Yates, and other items such as broadsides and a legal treatise by Thomas Wentworth printed in London in 1663.
Abraham Yates, Jr. was born In 1724 at Albany and died there in 1796. He was a radical whig politician who possessed considerable power and influence in northern New York. Related to the jurist Robert Yates he was, like him, an active revolutionary patriot and anti-federalist. As pamphleteers they shared the pen-name, The Rough Hewer. (See Dict. of American Biography, p. 601-602.)
The collection consists of correspondence, 1754-1825, of Abraham Yates, Jr., George Clinton, Robert Livingston, Jr., Christopher Yates, Robert Yates, Abraham Lansing, and others, concerning the activities of Abraham Yates Jr. as surveyor, Lawyer, Land speculator, sheriff of Albany political colleague and adversary, pamphleteer, anti-federalist, chairman of the Albany Committee of Correspondence, provincial congressman from Albany, Chairman of the convention that drafted the first New York State constitution, state senator, and mayor of Albany. There also are a letter-book, 1779-1782, relating to his office as commissioner for congressional loans to New York State, essays of Abraham Yates, Jr. on the constitution, speeches to delegates to congress, notes for his histories of New York and Albany, papers relating to the Manor of Rensselaerwyck, and to the Albany Committee of Correspondence, some indentures, mortgages, accounts, legal papers, official documents, broadsides relating to Philip Schuyler as a candidate for Senate, Federaoso and Aaron Burr, and support for Jay and Van Rensselaer, and a photograph of a painting of Abraham Yates Jr. The bulk of the collection was bequeathed to Victor Hugo Paltsits who donated it to the library.
1917, 1919, Received from Howard Townsend, 1917 Victor Hugo Paltsits, 1919
Clinton, George, 1739-1812; Lansing, Abraham; Livingston, Robert, 1718-1775; Wentworth, Thomas, 1568?-1628; Yates, Abraham, 1724-1796; Yates, Christopher C., 1778?-1848; Yates, Robert, 1738-1801; New York (State). Convention of the Representatives (1776-1777); United States; Real property -- New York (State); Photographs; Albany (N.Y.) -- History; Albany (N.Y.) -- Politics and government; New York (State) -- Constitution; New York (State) -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; New York (State) -- Politics and government -- To 1775; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; United States -- Politics and government -- 1775-1783; United States -- Politics and government -- To 1775; Pamphleteers; Politicians
- Correspondence
  - 1754-1786 (Folder 1)
  - 1787-1825 (Folder 2)
  - letter-book relating to the work of Yates at Commissioner of the Continental Loan Office for the state of New York, 1779 October 31-1782 August 11 (Folder 2)
  - journal/copybook, 1754-1758 (Folder 2)
- Writings, notes, and speeches
  - Essays (Folder 3)
    Essays on the Constitution; essays on various political subjects; notes on proceedings in Congress, 1774, Oct. 21-1775, Sept. 25; speeches to the delegates to Congress, 1786; The Rough Hewer manuscript.
  - Notes for a history of New York; notes on early histories or New York and Albany; notes on ancient revolutions of New York; unsorted notes (Folder 4)
  - Papers (Folder 5)
    Papers relating to the Manor of Rensselaerwyck; papers relating to the Supreme Court; Charter of Albany, N. Y.; papers of the Albany Committee of Correspondence; legal papers; mortgages; official documents, last wills and testaments; indentures; accounts; broadsides; and a photograph of a painting of Abraham Yates, Jr. ["The Office and duty of executors: or, A treatise of wills and and executors"] 1663, printed in London Wentworth vol. 1.
  - Slipcase Notes concerning the early history of N. Y, 1601-1761
- CHRONOLOGICAL LIST
  - 1. Schuyler, Pieter (Mayor- of Albany). A reply to Dom. Godevridue van Dell's application In regard to the highway. A. D. S. 2 p. folio, 1688 December 4
  - 2. Albany. Article from the Albany Argus of Dec, 10. 1899, relative to the population of Albany In 1697
  - 3. Ten Eyck, John (Recorder). Bill of costs In the suit of Andries Wies against Sybrant G. Van Schaik. D, S. 1 sma11 piece, no date, 1754 (probably)
  - 4. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yetta Esq., High Sheriff for the City and County of Albany. Congratulating him on his appointment as Sheriff and requesting that Patrick Magic he retained as "Jailkeeper", A. L, S. 1 p. folio, dated Manne, 1754 October 7
  - 5. Livingston. Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yates Junr. Esqr., High Sheriff of the City & County of Albany. Regretting the appointment of Thos. Worrel as Jail keeper. "As to Thos. Morrell perhaps you have not heard that I have promised him swiping, 1754 October 21
  - 6. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yetts, Esq., High Sheriff of the Comity of Albany. Requesting him to come down to Claverack and bring a "Writt" Kith him. Autograph letter signed 1 p. folio. dated Claverack, 1754 December 12
  - 7. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yets Junr. Esqr. att Albany. "I am told that there is again a Committee to come from Boston to view and layout lands, if not in my [doubt-] at least in the neighbourhood. I hope youll bring more friends a, 1755 January 31
  - 8. De Lansey, James, addressed to the Corporation of Albany, I have reason to hope that I shall be enabled to put your town In a better posture of defense than It has hitherto been". "You are sensible no great dependence is to be had on what the French In, 1755 February 10
  - 9. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yates Esqr., high Sheriff for the City & County of Albany. "On my Coming home I was informed that Some of my manner people took S new England men in my manner In arms A Carryed them to your Goal by Virtue, 1755 March 3
  - 10. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yetta Juar. Esqr., High Sheriff for the City & County of Albany, "With much difficulty I have at last catched Josiah Loomis, the ringleader find first beginner of the troubles with the Boston Government., 1755 April 14
  - 11. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yates Esqr., High Sheriff for the City & County of Albany. "Yours of the 25 ultima was delivered me yesterday at Tackanick were I have been to turn out my rebellious Tenants A pulled down their houses, w, 1755 May 2
  - 12. Livingston, Robert, Junr., to Abraham Yates Junr. "I am just, ready to set out for Boston from whence I have recd 2 letters that my son Phillip is in a declining State. I am much pleased to hear that your Corporation received General Shirly in a Body, 1755 July 16
  - 13. Hardy, Sir Charles, to Abraham Yates Junr. Esqr, Refers to the Lieut. Governor's Proclamation & orders Yates to apprehend A carry to Goal all persons in his Bailiwick guilty of Desertion. L. S. 1 p. quarto, dated New York, 1755 September 11
  - 14. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yates Esq., High Sheriff for the City & County of Albany. "I find that you have sent Patrick down to Consult me. I have reason to believe that he does not intend to Execute that precept you mention", Aut, 1756 February 9
  - 15. Swart, Dirck, addressed to Abraham Yates Junr. Esqr. at Albany. Referring to 5 Plates sent up to Yates by Esq. Fonda's Sloop, Also Bill for same, oblong strip In Dirck Swart's autograph. Autograph letter signed 1 p. quarto, dated Manner Livingston, 1756 March 18
  - 16. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yetts Esqr. at Albany. Relating to some escapee from Goal and the best measures to take for the recapture of one called Shoemaker, Autograph letter signed 1 p folio, dated Manner Livingston, 1756 March 31
  - 17. Murray, Joseph, addressed to William Corry Esquire, Attorney at Law In Albany. Relating to various legal cases, L. S. 2 p. folio, dated New York, 1756 August 2
  - 18. Banyar, George[DOUBT-], addressed to Abraham Yates Jun. Esq., high Sheriff of the City and County of Albany. Mentions Mr. Silvester. "I apprehend your office of Sheriff will be looked on as incompatible with that of an Attorney". Autograph letter sign, 1756 October 4
  - 19. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yetts Esqr., High Sheriff of the City & County of Albany. Relating to Judgments against rebellious Tenants. "We have agreed to give the Govr. L 1800 pr. annum but he Refuses to take it & Insists on havin, 1756 October 20
  - 20. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yetts Esqr., High Sheriff of the City & County of Albany, "I returned last night; from New York & shall be glad to see you here the beginning of the next week to execute the Judgments", Autograph letter, 1756 November 16
  - 21. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yetta Esqr., High Sheriff for tha City & County of Albany. "I wrote you on my arrival from New York & desiring you to come down to Execute the Judgment a of Court for turning my Rebellious Tenants out of, 1756 November 23
  - 22. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yetts Esqr., High Sheriff for the City & County of Albany. "I have bean threatened by Van Golden's Sons to be murdered & burnt down, of which I gott an affidavit of a Sheffield man who heard them say it., 1756 December 15
  - 23. Worth, Johann Jacob, addressed to Mats. Abraham Yates, Sheriff lieving in Albany, Reminding him of his promise to send the under-sheriff to Schoharie. A, L. S. In Dutch, 1 p. folio, dated Schocharie, 1757 April [DOUBT-]
  - 24. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yetts Esqr., High Sheriff for the City & County of Albany. "Mrs. Livingston told me that She heard the Rebels were again looking out & marking out farms In My manner" A, L. S. 1 p. folio, dated Manor Liv, 1757 April 14
  - 25. Wendell, Harmanus. Draft of his will. Signed by Jacop Pruyn. John Ja. Lansingh & Pet. Silvester as witnesses. D. S. 2 p. folio, 1757 April 13
  - 26. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yetts Esqr., High Sheriff for City & County of Albany. Repeating the request in a former letter and desiring him to come down without any Loss of time. Autograph letter signed 1 p. folio, dated Manor Liv, 1757 April 27
  - 27. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yetts Junr. Esqr., High Sheriff att Albany. "Sir, Charles told me I should apply to you when ever any attempts were made to Settle or take possession of my Lands". Autograph letter signed 1 p. folio, dat, 1757 May 9
  - 28. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yetts Junr. Esqr., High Sheriff for the City, & County of Albany. Relating to the release from Goal of John Van Gelden & his son. "I fear he will come & burn me down or waylay & kill me, at least he will, 1757 May 15
  - 29. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yetts Junr, Esqr., High Sheriff for the City A County of Albany. "I am on my Guard & you'll I suppose not be surprised when you hear that I have Shett him, which I am determined to do the first time I se, 1757 May 18
  - 30. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yetts Junr, Esqr., Sheriff of the County of Albany. Enclosing a Proclamation received from Mr. Banyard.. Autograph letter signed 1 p. quarto, dated Manor Livingston, 1757 June 23
  - 31. Livingston, Robert, Junr., to Abraham Yates Junr. Refers to Peter Dow's illness & to Coll. Schuyler. "I often long to hear the news of your town & of the army, which I most generally have Imperfect". Autograph letter signed 1 p. folio, dated Manor Liv, 1757 July 3
  - 32. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yetts Junr. Esqr., High Sheriff of the City & County of Albany. Refers to John Van Gelden'e demand for the restitution of hie horse, saddle, bridle. Guns &c. which had been taken from him when he was com, 1757 July 6
  - 33. Livingston, Robert, Junr., to Abraham Yates Junr. Interesting letter referring to the French & Indian War. "Am heartily glad to hear that the Summerset man of war has been. so fortunate as to take two French Ships with 300 men & is 89000 Sterling, but, 1757 July 19
  - 34. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yetts Esqr, att Albany. Inquiring whether Mr. Bleeker intended to come down to run a line for him. Autograph letter signed 1 p. folio, dated Manor Livingston, 1757 November 5
  - 35. Egbertse, Egbert. His complaint against Alexander McLane. D. 2 p. folio, dated Mayor's Court, 1758
  - 36. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yates Junr. Esqr., High Sheriff for the City & County of Albany, Interesting letter relating to the expedition against Ticonderoga, "I see General Abercromby & Lord How have made application to Coll. Ren, 1758 February 17
  - 37. Wendell, Henry I., addressed to Abraham Yates Esq., Sheriff in Albany. "Lord how has Ordered me Immediately to Proceed With my Company and complete It upon the Mohawk River". Autograph letter signed 1 p. quarto, dated Albany, 1758 April 4
  - 38. Livingston, Robert, Junr., to Abraham Yates Junr. "I have been at [doubt-] to assist my Couz's Robert & Henry Livingston in their Election". Autograph letter signed, 1 p. folio, dated Manor Livingston, 1759 January 11
  - 39. Livingston, Robert, Junr., to Abraham Yates Junr. Interesting letter relating to the politics of Albany, "Both parties have acted impolitic & without that honour & generosity with which citizens ought to treat, one the other, at all times & more Espec, 1759 February 10
  - 40. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yates Esqr., High Sheriff of City & County of Albany. Refers to the death of "our old friend, Cap. Winne". "Lett me know what news you have & where the greatest Strength of our Army is gone, Northward or, 1759 June 8
  - 41. Livingston, Robert, Junr, addressed to Abraham Yates Esqr., High Sheriff for the City, & County of Albany. Interesting letter relating to the French & Indian war. "I am in a Continual dread least I should hear of the French Fleets getting to Quebec be, 1759 June 15
  - 42. Banyar, [doubt-], addressed to Abraham Yates Junr. Esqr., High Sheriff of Albany Enclosing a copy of the. Naturalisation Act & mentioning Sir William Johnson' tenants. "If among the others there are any whom you think really unable to pay the Fee on a, 1759 July 16
  - 43. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yates Esqr., High Sheriff for City & County of Albany Interesting letter relating to the French & Indian War. "I beg you to write me the particulars of Niagara & How it came about that Sir William had th, 1759 August 6
  - 44. Livingston, Robert, Junr., to Abraham Yates Junr. Interesting letter referring to Gen. Amherst, Sir William Johnson, Gen. Wolfe, Admiral Rodney & others. "In my opinion If we do not take Canada we shall give very little by this war". Autograph letter, 1759 August 9
  - 45. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yates Junr. Esqr. att Albany. "I have seen the articles of Surrender of Quebec in our papers, which are also Extraordinary and much of a piece with those of Guadeloupe, neither of which please me. I do n, 1759 November 24
  - 46. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yates Junr. Esqr. att Albany. Refers to his lot in the "Saratoga Patent". "The French officers make a long tarry on our frontiers, provisions are more plenty there then at Canada", Autograph letter signe, 1760 January 3
  - 47. Livingston, Robert, Junr., to Abraham Yates Junr, Referring to Yates having been removed from office by his enemies. "They now begin with me, the Great & mighty Coll, has seazed upon my horses and Sleds". A, L. S. 1 p. folio, dated Manor Livingston, 1760 January 24
  - 48. Livingston, Robert, Junr, to Abraham Yates Junr. "God Grant we may Soon take all Canada & keep It while the world Stands, that we may be relieved from Sundry petto Tyrants who rule with a Rod of Iron the best Subjects the King of Great Britain has in, 1760 February 8
  - 49. Cobham, William, addressed to Abraham Yates Esq. at Albany. Stating his account against Lewis Deluxe & putting same in Yates' hands for collection. Autograph letter signed 2 p. folio, dated New York, 1760 February 11
  - 50. Livingston, Robert, Junr., to Abraham Yates Junr. Refers to the Albany Library. "God Grant us Success that the Enemy may be obliged to Sue for a peace before the End of this year". Autograph letter signed, 1 p. folio, dated Manor Livingston, 1760 February 29
  - 51. Cobham, William, addressed to Abraham Yates Esq. at Albany. "Mr Hugh Gain has sent all his Accent. to Mr. McComb at Albany". Autograph letter signed 1 p. quarto, dated New York, 1760 March 11
  - 52. Van Eps, John E., addressed to Mr. Abraham Yates, attorney at Law at Albany, to the care of Joseph Yates at Sehonechdadie. Mentions Andries Gardenier & his brother Jacob. Autograph letter signed in Dutch, 1 p. folio, dated Cagenuwago, 1760 May 22
  - 53. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yates Junr. Esqr. att Albany. Very Interesting letter containing war news. "I have heard that the French have Raised the Siege of Quebec on the appearance of our fleet. I shall order a good fat Oxen to b, 1760 May 30
  - 54. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Mr, Abraham Yates Junr., Merchant in Albany. Refers to the Albany election, certain lands in Saratoga Patent, making mention, of Col. Bradstreet, the Bleeckers, Ten Broecks and De Ridders, & closing as follows:, 1760 July 17
  - 55. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yates Junr. Esqr. att Albany. Refers to the damage to crops caused by heavy rains all the way from Fishkill up to Albany. "I expect our Army is now in motion This is a time we ought above all others to h, 1760 August 11
  - 56. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Mr. Abraham Yates Junr. att Albany. Refers to the good news that "our Armies are new In possession of all Canada". Also mention Yates desirs to again obtain the office of Sheriff. A, L. S. 1 p. folio, dated Mano, 1760 September 3
  - 57. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yates Esqr. att Albany I have this day wrote to my Brother Philip & William to wait on his Honr. the President and to desire the favour of him in my name to appoint you Sheriff for the Ensuring; year. "A, 1760 September [doubt-]
  - 58. Whitney, Thomas, addressed to Abraham Yates Esq, at Alban;. Asking him. to "take Gear" of two "Rites" Autograph letter signed 1 p. folio, dated Clouvriack, 1760 October 6
  - 59. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Mr. Abraham Yates Junr., Merchant In Albany. "I Long to hear what voyages your Albany Gentlemen have made to Canada. I also want to know how the Troops are to be disppsed of now the war is at an End in our Quart, 1760 October 13
  - 60. Whitney, Thomas, to Abraham Yates Junr. Telling him he had settled his Action with Robert Noble. Autograph letter signed 1 p. folio, dated Clouvarieck, 1760 October 29
  - 62. Yates, Abraham, Junr. Draft of letter in his autograph. Relative to the sale of certain lands. Autograph letter signed 2 p. folio, dated Albany, 1760 October 29
  - 63. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yates Junr, Eaqr. att Albany Refers to the sale of lands in the Saratoga Patent by the Bleekers, Mr, Ten Broeck & Shuyler & "your old uncle Killiaen. "I imagine your City must Inlarge that way, while no, 1760 November 7
  - 63. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yates Esq. att Albany. "But how your uncle Killiaen will sell any I am at a lose to know, as I heard some time ago that there was some difficulty in his Tittle". Autograph letter signed 1 p. folio, dated, 1760 November 13
  - 64. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yates Junr. Esqr. att Albany. Refers to Killiaen De Ridder's title to lands in the Saratoga Patent. "I hear it hinted from New York that we are going to have an Expedition, this winter to the Massasappie, 1760 December 10
  - 65. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yates Junr. Esqr. In Albany Refers to a petition addressed by the Corporation of the City of Albany to "the President & Council". "I Congratulate you on the Victory Lately gained by the King of Prussia, 1765 January 22
  - 66. Livingston, Robert, Junr., to Abraham Yates Junr. Referring to the election in Albany & mentioning various candidates. "If you are Inclinable to Sett up with Mr. Abraham Ten Broeck, whom I Look upon to be without any flattery the two best Qualified in, 1761 February 4
  - 67. Livingston, Robert, Junr., to Abraham Yates Junr. Referring to the coming Election & the difference of opinion existing between Yates & Tan Broeck. Mentions Sir William Johnson, "who undoubtedly has great Interest". "As for my part while my friends ar, 1761 February 6
  - 68. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Abraham Yates Junr. Esqr. att Albany. Refers to Yates standing for the coming election. "The Camps will not move to an Election without being payed for- their time at 4 e/ pr. man. The Gentlemen of the other Sid, 1761 February 8
  - 69. Livingston, Robert, Junr. Unsigned draft, copy of a letter sent by Livingston to Messrs. Douw & Ten Eyck. It was enclosed In Livingston's letter to Yates, bearing date Feb. 16, 1761. "As my friend; Mr. Ab, Yates wrote me. the 4 Current that he Intende
  - 70. Yates G Junr., addressed to [DOUBT-] Junr., Merchant att Albany. Refers to dishonorable methods used at elections. "I see you are like to have new Troubles upon your Corporation for Incroachments by the Township of Schenectady. Autograph letter signed, 1761 February 16
  - 71. Yates, Abraham, Junr. Draft of letter to Robert Livingston in his autograph. [DOUBT-], interesting letter relating to the Election In Albany. Mentions Abraham Ten Broeck's dishonorable conduct toward Yates, Sir William Johnson's influence ac. 6 p, fol, 1761 February 16
  - 72. Yates, Abraham, Junr. "We are apprehensive that we will be obliged to contend with the Inhabitants of Schonectady about the Bounds and Jurisdiction of our City". Endorsed; "A. Yates Junrs., observation on Limits of the City 1761". D. 4 p. folio, dated, 1761 February 21
  - 73. Livingston, Robert, Junr., addressed to Mr. Abraham Yates Junr., Merchant att Albany. Refers to Yates failure at the recent Election. "You have now experienced what dependence there is on that frail Creature Called man. I hope however you have not pai, 1761 March 26